Guide to the Morris and Dorothy Margolin Film Collection, 1947-1982 and undated RL.10157
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Films, 1947-1976; 1
  - S.S. New Amsterdam, France, 1959, 15; 27.11 minutes
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 27.11 minutes (Box 2, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0015)
  - Puerto Rico and Jamaica, 1959, 16; 21.28 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0016 Puerto Rico, Jamaica, 1959 Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color 21.28 minutes
    • title card: "Islands in the Sun: Puerto Rico, Jamaica, St. Thomas" • Dorothy and friends (possibly family?) sunbathing, hamming it up for the camera • people relaxing in waterfalls • underexposed, hard to see • woman climbs into car • funicular • aerial views of lush landscape and ocean • fellow travelers outside of hotel? • British flag; probably in Jamaica • lush landscape • travelers climb into car outside of hotel? • men ride bicycles, pull goats on a leash • young girl on side of the road • sign: "Jamaica Inn" • palm tree and ocean • resort, beach scenes • street scenes, shot from a moving car • monument • houses, shot from a moving car • uniformed man in front of constabulary station • woman selling produce at roadside stand • traffic jam? cars stopped, people gathered • another shot of produce stand • group standing outside of bus • police car • cars stationary on road • people stand on the roadside, shot from inside a car • woman carries a bundle on her head • man rides by on donkey • women carry baskets on their heads • street scenes • fellow traveler beside fenced garden • fellow traveler in the middle of the road, vehicle approaches from behind • street scenes • sign: "JAA Bog Walk" • shots of unidentified building with fenced garden in front • shots of "Tom Cringle's Cotton Tree," including sign • cart hauling palm fronds, shot from behind • street scenes, shot from inside car • shops • women waving straw hats • traffic cop directs traffic • sidewalk and street scenes, including fellow travelers • directional sign: "Victoria Crafts Market" • street and sidewalk scenes • group of children walk toward the camera • young girl and father pose for camera • young boys play on the sidewalk, hamming it up for the camera • street scenes from car, including traffic cops • fellow travelers stand beneath sign: "Welcome to Victoria Crafts Market: The All-Jamaican Shopping Centre" • boats on the water, at dock • woman embellishing hats • advertisement: Welcome to Jamaica See the Exciting Mid-Day Native Floor Show at New Bamboo Club • fellow travelers climb into car • Dorothy poses for camera in garden • Dorothy and friend pose in front of flower garden that spells out "Welcome to Hope" • garden, flowers • patio seating at restaurant, fellow travelers and other tourists drink, eat, dance • Dorothy and friends balance drinks on their heads • Dorothy and friends drink • traditionally dressed Jamaican musicians play and dance for tourists on patio • lots of dancing! • man walks to car, stormy day • life preserver: Arawak Hotel, Jamaica, B.W.I. • exteriors of the Arawak Hotel • fellow travelers sunbathe on the beach • birds fly overhead • Dorothy and fellow travelers walk from beach to hotel pool • each poses with life preserver framing their face • overexposed shot of ocean • fellow travelers swimming in ocean • boats in water: sailboat, glass bottom boat, etc. • beach filled with beachgoers, pier • pool at the Arawak Hotel? • Dorothy? in swimming cap swims out to friend on raft • the Margolins? runs out into ocean together, swims back to shore • another couple does the same • buffet meal • hotel pool • back to the mealtime • sign: "670 New York" • sign: "Avianca Colombian National Airway" • shots of Avianca plane on tarmac • interiors of plane, underexposed • shots of clouds, propeller, sunset from airplane window
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 21.28 minutes (Box 2, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0016)
  - Aruba, 1962, 17; 12.47 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0017 Aruba, 1962 Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color 12.47 minutes
    • three people sitting in seats at an airport • people waiting in airport • debarking from airplane • beach • tourists at hotel pool • sailboat • churches • buildings • harbor • cars • traffic • outdoor produce stand • stores • shops • women walking with baskets on heads • esplanade • water skiing • native barge • man standing and paddling in a small "canoe" filled with green bananas • people walking a dog down a side walk
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 12.47 minutes (Box 2, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0017)
  - Italy (Naples, Taormina), Israel, Cristoforo Colombo (ship), 1964, 18; 43.37 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0018 Italy (Naples, Taormina), Israel, Cristoforo Colombo (ship), 1964 Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color 43.37 minutes
    • life preserver: C. Colombo Genova • travelers on deck of ocean liner Cristoforo Colombo • men in dinghy trying to sell goods to people on ocean liner, goods travel up a rope port • Pompeii • ruins, museum • Napoli • streets scenes • mosque • children • piazza • cars • traffic • girl in first communion dress • shops • stores • cafes • view of mountain • hilltop park • tourists on beach • Israel: • border guards • people working in fields • sign: "Yad Mordekhai" • street scenes • outdoor market • donkey cart • cars • stores • shops • traffic • beach • hotel • archeological sites • people in orchard • ruins of Roman baths with curative waters • synagogue • sign: "Eastern Bridge" • Cesarea • playing games with people at a settlement • construction sites and new buildings • palace, including grounds • mosques • aerial view of harbor city • sign: "General Exhibition of Safad Artists" • children • Jerusalem: • street scenes • aerial view of city • sign: "King David's Tomb" • sign: "Chamber of Destruction" • Mount of Olives • Mount Zion • buildings • roads • university campus • students • couple walking arm and arm on a curved sidewalk
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 43.37 minutes (Box 2, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0018)
  - Yugoslavia and Greece, 1964, 19; 11.48 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0019 Yugoslavia, Greece, 1964 Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color 11.48 minutes
    • title card: "Vagabonds in Foreign Lands" • title card: Produced by Margolin • title card: Directed by Margolin • title card: Costumes by Margolin • title card: Casting by Margolin • title card: Music Sound by Margolin • title card: Financed by Margolin • title card: Photography by Margolin • Cast / Morris - Fuehrer / Kal - A Runner / Eleanor - Prime Minister / Dorothy - Shlepalong • boats in harbor in Greece • Dorothy on boat with Kal? • boat sets sail, views of the water and shore • Dorothy and Eleanor? on deck • Dorothy poses with view of city behind her • views of towns and harbors from the boat • street scenes, including enormous pelican • small boat on the water • man rides donkey up and out of tunnel • boat docks • buildings on the mountainside • man rolls barrel along street • harbor scenes • countryside, including mountains • Kal?, Dorothy, Eleanor? exit museum? one at a time • Acropolis • Dorothy poses at the Acropolis, then at Parthenon • Morris poses at the Parthenon • Dorothy walks into the frame, pans to Greek flag in distance • close-up of Parthenon columns • aerial views of Athens • close-up of Greek flag • aerial views of Athens • views of the Parthenon • amphitheatre • beach and seaside buildings • street scenes • scenes from street market • close-ups on produce • Dorothy? walks down narrow street • man gets his hair cut • street scenes, including street sweeper • Dorothy walks down narrow street • street scenes • Dorothy talks to man on the street • city square • women balancing baskets on their head • school group? walks along street • street scenes • people at fountain • pigeons fly around square • women in traditional clothing • Dorothy stands on steps, pans to street and hillside • woman in blue dress walks down steps • man in uniform walks down steps
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 11.48 minutes (Box 2, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0019)
  - Japan, 1965, 20; 22.43 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0020 Japan, 1965 Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color 22.43 minutes
    • exterior of store camera at a 90 degree angle • city street scenes of native people dressed in Western clothing and traditional Japanese clothing • stores • shops • outdoor sculptures • monuments • Rodin sculptures • river • kites • sign: "Uyeno Seiyoken" • office buildings • cars • traffic • park • sign: "Buddhist Temple: Kotoku-In Monastery Kamakura" • school group at the temple • houses • boats/junks on land • pagodas • view from train • funicular up a mountain • man boiling eggs in a hot spring • tourist ferry boat • boats in harbor • train station • school children • women in kimonos • street parade • museum commemorating victims of Hiroshima • hot springs • formal procession • pagoda
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 22.43 minutes (Box 2, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0020)
  - Bangkok, Hong Kong, 1965, 21; 28.03 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0021 Bangkok, Hong Kong, 1965 Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color 28.03 minutes
    • "Hong Kong Water Tours" flap flying from mast of boat • Hong Kong • wooden ferry boat • boats in harbor • view of skyline from the boat • sign: "Kowloon Public Pier" • harbor crowded with houseboats • people fishing from small boat • street scenes • people walking • modern hotel with beach and golf course • Bangkok • houses • sign: "Tiger pagoda- exterior and detail" • aerial view of city • street scenes • hotels • shops • stores • restaurants • apartment houses • monkey • outdoor café • houseboats • flooded rice patties • boats • sights of other boats, structures, houses and people as seen from a boat going down river • people swimming and bathing in the river • vendors selling merchandise from their small boats • Buddhist temple, including interior, exterior, grounds • Buddhist monks • buildings and another boat on river viewed from a traveling boat
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 28.03 minutes (Box 2, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0021)
  - Hawaii, Pakistan, Turkey, Portugal, 1965, 22; 25.22 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0022 Hawaii, Pakistan, Turkey, Portugal, 1965 Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color 25.22 minutes
    • palm trees • Hawaii • hula dance performance with guitar accompanists • group of tourists learn to hula dance • man climbing a palm tree • sailboats at the edge of beach • Pakistan? Turkey? • street market • vendors • street scenes • village huts outside of the city • oxen • houses • outdoor laundry • unidentified palace • camel • children • café on a beach • stores • shops • trams • boats • exterior and interior and grounds of palace or museum • sign: "Baghdad Kiosk" • men washing feet • temple or mosque? • monuments • obelisks • aerial view of coliseum, city, bay • street market • interior of airplane, flight attendants • Portugal • outdoor produce market • harbor • esplanade • fishermen repairing nets and boats • street scenes • exteriors of buildings • beach • town square • village life • women washing laundry • sign: "Convento de Santa Cruz dos Capuchos" • exteriors of Palacio Hotel
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 25.22 minutes (Box 3, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0022)
  - France (Paris, Deauville, the Riviera), 1967, 23; 33.08 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0023 France (Paris, Deauville, the Riviera), 1967 Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color 33.08 minutes
    • traffic circle in Paris, vehicles driving around an obelisk • buildings • traffic • cars • sign: "Place Vendome" • street scenes • scale models of ocean liners • sign: "Avenue De L'Opera" • L'Opera • Gendarme • shops • stores • cinema • film posters • apartment houses • street vendors • streetcar • construction workers • advertisements • sign: "Rue St. Honoré" • sign: "Boulevard St. Germain" • churches • Place St. Genevieve • Anti-Vietnam War and Anti-American posters • Seine River • Notre Dame • people on the banks of the Seine • Deauxville • street scenes • hotel • waterfront • harbor • shops • stores • buildings • cars • vehicles • traffic • café • horse and buggy • sign: "Avenue General De Gaulle" • New Golf Club in Deauville • statue honoring the dead of World War II • outdoor street market • beach • Paris • statue of Joan of Arc • cars • traffic • sign: "Rue de Rivoli" • Champs-élysées • outdoor sculptures • park • Arc De Triomphe • George V Hotel • Folies Bergère poster • cafés • sign: "Champs Elysees" • Maria Callas poster • Christian Dior boutique • Eiffel Tower • sign: "Rue De Seine" • tourist tour boat • church • University of Paris • sign: "Quai des Tuileries" • sign: "Rue de la Paix" • sign: "Boulevard des Capucines • sign: "Rue Danou" • French Riviera • palm trees and Paramount film posters • Cannes? • film posters and advertisements • outdoor beachfront café • people on the beach • airport • people boarding an airplane • boats in a harbor • fisherman unloading nets • photo shoot of a model in a bikini • Carlton Hotel • Chartres cathedral? • front of Chartres Cathedral
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 33.08 minutes (Box 3, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0023)
  - Michelangelo (ship), Morocco, and Italy (Venice), 1967, 24; 43.16 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0024 Morocco, Italy, 1967, 1967 Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color 43.16 minutes
    • prow of the ocean liner Michelangelo • people seeing off the ship from dock • crew working on ship • travelers on deck of ship • ship captain piloting ship • Port of Genoa • Morocco • buildings • hotel • street scenes • donkeys/mules • stores • shops • people filling up water at an outdoor faucet • men praying • mosque • outdoor street market • outdoor vendors • women in burkahs • traffic • acrobats performing on street • interior of mosque • aerial view of city • apartment houses • cemetery • castle or fortress • directional signs: Beni Mellal, Kasba Tadla, El Kelaa and Marrakesh • fields • sheep and herder • Marrakesh • children walking home from school • rug weavers at looms • sign: "Cooperative Artisanale D'Azrou" • village • houses • city street scenes • sign: "Arab Bank" • garden • sign: "Proprieté Jacque Majorelle" • village • laundry • sign: "Hotel La Mamounia" • parade or march • hotel pool • street performers • snake charmer • street dancers and musicians • sign: "Casbah" • Casbah garden • Venice • motorboat ride • view of Venice from canal • gondolas • breakfast on balcony • buildings • canals • palaces • bridges • sign: "Hotel Bauer Grunwald" • flags flying • beach • Doge's Palace • stores • shops • street scenes • artists painting at easels in piazza • interior of restaurant • café • advertisements • street vendors • pigeons • children and nuns in a procession • group of young people walking through a piazza
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 43.16 minutes (Box 3, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0024)
  - USSR, 1967, 25; 31.5 minutes
    This film does not appear to have been made by Morris Margolin; rather, it is likely that it is a documentary film acquired by the Margolins on their trip to the Soviet Union.
    - Reversal original, 16mm, sound, color, 31.5 minutes (Box 3, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0025)
  - Capri, Ethiopia, Nairobi, Kenya, Cape Town, Johannesburg, and safari, 1971 October, 26; 41.16 minutes
    RL10157-FS8-0001 Capri - Ethiopia - Nairobi, Kenya - Cape Town - Johannesburg - Safari, October 1971 Reversal original, Super 8mm, silent, color 41.16 minutes
    • flowers on windowsill, landscape from window • sign: "Servizio Motoscafi per la Grotta Azzurra" • street scenes, including Bar Grotta Azzurra • boats at dock • street scenes, including street vendor • boats and buildings along shore • close up on sign: "Servizio Motoscafi per la Grotta Azzurra / Andata e ritorno L. 300 • buildings near water, on cliff • beach from a distance • men on dock working with net • boats in harbor • woman fills bucket with water at spigot • street scenes, including cafes and shops • Dorothy sits near bottom of stairs • ships on the water • Dorothy and friend? walk with crowd toward camera • high-angle shots of people in canoes, boats near La Grotta Azzurra • people exit canoes, line for canoe rides • Dorothy and friend? in canoe • views of landscape • exteriors of a villa? • Dorothy under a covered walkway • views of landscape • walkway flanked by trees • sign: "San Michele di Axel Munthe" • Dorothy walks out of doorway • plaque about Axel Munthe (in Italian) • two people tend to garden • café • clock tower • street scenes, including Dorothy • building: Hotel Quisiana • scenes at the dock, includes sign: "Diretto Sorrento" • Dorothy and friends wait with luggage • views of harbor and boats, shot from boat • garden or park? in Ethiopia • buildings • street scenes • crowd on hillside • livestock • street scenes, including Dorothy, people gathering? at roundabout • two men shake hands • well-dressed young people line-up • plaque: in Amharic? • plaque: "His Imperial Majesty Haile Selassie the First Emperor of Ethiopia In Order to Promote and Improve the Services of Posts and Telecommunications for the Benefit of His People Inaugurated These Buildings on This 2nd Day of November 1969 on the Thirty Ninth Year of His Reign" • exteriors of buildings • sign: "Minister of State" • street scenes, construction • exteriors of building, parking lot • street scenes, crowd gathered • Dorothy amongst the crowd • crowd gathered around street performance • sign: "Terefe Guta House Rent & Real Estate Broker" • exteriors of buildings, street scenes • close-up on painting, underexposed • Ethiopian flag flaps in distance, behind trees • scenes of impoverished area • buildings, mountains off in the distance • lion statue • man in traditional clothing • H.I.M. Menelik mausoleum • statue • exterior shots of unidentified building • close-ups on stained glass with religious motifs • building under construction? • exteriors of unidentified buildings, gardens • Dorothy walks toward the camera • sign: "Haile Selassie I University" • exteriors of buildings, presumably at the university • Dorothy on the roadside, sign behind her reads: "You are now entering Kenya" • sign: "Nairobi Hebrew Congregation Services" • exteriors of synagogue • street scenes • sign: "University of Nairobi" • exteriors of unidentified buildings • Dorothy walks around sculpture, toward camera • close-ups of sculptures • plaque: "In grateful remembrance of Dr. R.K. Yajnik" • exteriors of buildings • building: University of Nairobi • street scenes • creek • cityscape • giraffes • sign: "White Grass Ridge / Beware of Lions" • zebras, other wildlife • scenes from the savanna • primates (baboons?), one sits on the hood of a car • hippos in the water • locals and tourists on a path • antelope? • sign: "Hyaena Dam / Narogomon Dam" • ostrich • lioness walks from behind van • landscape shots • warthogs • gazelle? • running ostrich • giraffe • city skyline, buildings • sign: "Golden City Hotel" • street scenes • sign: "Jewish Guild War Memorial" (Johannesburg, South Africa?) • street scenes • building with scaffolding • street scenes, exteriors of buildings • Hotel Monte Carlo • Barclays Bank • men loading cargo • Tollman Towers • street scenes • Dorothy window-shops • street scenes, including Foschini, Woolworths • skyline of Johannesburg? • Dorothy and friends in a neighborhood • street scenes • Johannesburg airport • clouds, countryside, towns from plane • plane lands in Cape Town? • skyline • street scenes • teacher and schoolgirls walk by • sign on truck: Katz & Co. / High Class Confectioners / Wedding Cakes & Pastries our Specialty • bus, street scenes • traffic cop directs traffic outside of the Board of Executors • exteriors of unidentified building • street scenes, exteriors of buildings • sign: "Twenty Four Hours of Prayer for Racial Harmony in St. Georges Cathedral" • Houses of Parliament in Cape Town • statue of Victoria R.I. • sign: "Government Ave" • garden, men working near statue • sign: "Art-Gallery / Museum" • unidentified church? • Table Mountain • aerial view of Cape Town, including the harbor • Jameson Memorial Hall • Dorothy at University of Cape Town? • young people on lawn, steps • chauffeur leans against black car • young people on lawn, steps • cars parked on street • sign: "University of Cape Town" • unidentified structure on hillside • street scenes, buildings • boat: Good Hope Castle • industrial scenes of port • billboard for Ackermans, "A family friendly store where you get... Value for your Money" • people, boats in Cape Town harbor and port • building: Port Offices - Hawekantore • seagulls • boat: H. Sawyer, Cape Town • street scenes • aerial views of city and surrounding area, including the ocean • Dorothy and man look out at city • plaque: "This cornerstone was placed in position in the House of God at sea point Cape Town by the right Hon. J.C. Smuts P.C., M.P., Minister of Justice" • exteriors of buildings, close-up on door • Castle of Good Hope • sign: "Visitors to the Castle / William Fehr Collection Military Museum / Enquiries" • café • school group walks past the camera • aerial views of oceanfront and ocean, city and mountains • sign: "Chapmans Peak" • sign: "Cape of Good Hope Nature Reserve" • scenery shot from moving car • sign: "Cape Town 37" • monkeys? peek in through vent on bus • Dorothy poses with ocean in background • sign: "Whites / Men & Women / Toilets" • people climb hill toward unidentified building • sign: "Toilets / Non Whites / Men & Women" • sign: "Viewpoint" • views of cliffs, ocean • unidentified building on hilltop
    - Reversal original, Super 8mm, silent, color, 41.16 minutes (Box 3, Film-reel RL10157-FS8-0001)
  - TreeTops, Tanzania, Kenya, Safari Club / Safari, Ngorongoro Crater, Durban, Zulu Land, 1971 October, 27; 29.41 minutes
    RL10157-FS8-0002 TreeTops - Tanzania - Kenya - Safari Club / Safari - Ngorongoro Crater - Durban - Zulu Land, October 1971 Reversal original, Super 8mm, silent, color 29.41 minutes